<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-04T15:03:41-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">zmagg’s blog</title><subtitle>zmagg's blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why return to RC? (and some notes on what I spent week 3 &amp;amp; 4 at RC doing)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/12/09/why-return-rc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why return to RC? (and some notes on what I spent week 3 &amp;amp; 4 at RC doing)" /><published>2021-12-09T18:16:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-09T18:16:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/12/09/why-return-rc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/12/09/why-return-rc.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-return-to-recurse-center&quot;&gt;Why return to Recurse Center?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing y’all from North Carolina where I’m visiting friends and family. Coming back here always makes me think of the phrase “You can’t go home again”, after the Thomas Wolfe novel set here. For me as a programmer, Recurse Center has been my home since I was last in batch in 2013. I came in as a young programmer who had worked in the tech industry but wasn’t sure if the tech industry was the right place for them and I left feeling like I should at least give it more of a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Thomas Wolfe novel is maybe not culturally relevant still, many family, friends, and strangers asked me why I was going back to do something I had done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t super sure myself when starting to be honest. Some of it was motivated by wanting some structure around my day to day life immediately after leaving the rigid structure of a day to day corporate job, as well as wanting to be around other people going through a similar experience and time in their life. All of this has been FANTASTIC, which I’ve shared in prior posts. Some of  my motivation was also emotional though. I’m working through what it looks like to keep going in the tech industry and this is where I first found the space to really give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that’s surprised me has been the permission to be a beginner again as well as the energy that comes from being around other people who are also doing something new !! to them. I spent the first two weeks building astronomically accurate sun art in Typescript, none of which I knew how to do before getting started. (( Sidenote: still have to finish this project. )) Great teams and workplaces can give space for even experts to ask beginner style questions, but for the most part for the last few years I’ve been in roles where I’ve been expected to ramp up fast and lead from what I’ve seen before. It’s been a real joy to get to just do stuff I really don’t know how to do. In the context of RC it’s also been fun to see how much faster I am at problem solving than I was 8 years ago when I was last here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempting-to-teach-from-what-you-know&quot;&gt;(Attempting to) teach from what you know&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I asked &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/zmagg/status/1461450620628451328&quot;&gt;on twitter&lt;/a&gt; how people who had worked in the industry for 15+ years kept it feeling exciting and new. A lot of people said teaching and mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortuitously for me as I navigate trying to continue in this industry, I got the opportunity to do some more structured teaching recently. My friend Lindsey Kuper asked if I’d give a guest lecture for her undergrad distributed systems class at UC Santa Cruz, so I spent week 3 at RC prepping a talk for this class. This is the kind of teaching that I’ve always found most challenging–teaching to an audience where you have a BIG experience gap. I’ve always found it easier to teach people something I’ve just learned, or to teach people who have worked on similar systems and just need to know the specific details that differ. The talk was pretty well received though, and it seemed like the undergrads were engaged and following the material for the first 90% of the talk, which is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1FBoSJzwLbG4f9otW8Ki3nj84BesKyr-dnam0EApEFxA/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt; are here, and I’ll be giving it again at Recurse Center in January, where I will maybe record it. Content is some old systems design decisions Slack made, as well as two old incidents we had around the distributed database I worked on there. Side note: I hope that the content is old enough that Slack is cool with me talking about it externally, but uh, if you (still) work at Slack and you’re reading this and you think I should’ve checked with someone, let me know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In prepping for the talk, I chose the incidents to highlight some things related to what was in the course curriculum–namely replication, sharding, and consensus. One thing I would’ve wanted to know more about as an undergrad in a class-like setting is how these decisions actually show up in the real world. Something that I’ve learned while working is that although some systems design decisions are made at the whiteboard level weighing tradeoffs ahead of time, others you only find out about after you run your system and hit an incident. And then you get to make a decision about just how much time you’re willing to invest in fixing the problem you’ve created, and that can dictate as much of the solution space as anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, those are just my feelings about this talk. I’ll attempt to post a lightly edited transcript version of the talk to this blog soon so that people who don’t like watching videos (like me) can get something out of the material too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Why return to Recurse Center?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Week 2 at RC (The sun part 2)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/12/week2-rc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week 2 at RC (The sun part 2)" /><published>2021-11-12T14:37:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-11-12T14:37:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/12/week2-rc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/12/week2-rc.html">&lt;p&gt;Gosh, when did I last update y’all? It’s been a week! Here are some things I’ve been up to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;from-3d-to-2d&quot;&gt;From 3D to 2D&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project at RC has been to model the sun’s path over the course of the year so that it can be used to help plan garden plots! Also so that I can learn something about frontend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, while I ported some functions to calculate a sun’s elevation / azimuth (degrees away from North from the perspective of the viewer) to Typescript, the act of working on this port caused my project to spawn some side project ideas. I want to make some astronomically accurate art with these calculations! I was especially inspired by what people in my batch have been doing with p5.js, so I’ve been using that this week. My idea is to represent the sun’s phase in the style of how moon phase posters/calendars look. Here’s where I’m at right now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/11112021/sungood.gif&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elevation and location of the sun is chosen based on the hard coded date/location– Berkeley CA on November 11 2021. Next I’m going to place multiple of these from different months of the year in a grid and let the user choose a location. Also…maybe shadows? Also…maybe finalizing the color palette instead of randomizing it? If I stick with randomizing though, I’m going to move over to HSB mode. Bonnie in my batch recommendd this &lt;a href=&quot;https://tylerxhobbs.com/essays/2016/working-with-color-in-generative-art&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; on HSB vs. RGB  which was super instructive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some bloopers, for your enjoyment. They’ve been hilarious to accidentally make, nothing like hitting save and seeing the sun go upside down.  Still working on the art piece, but I’ll share as I go next week and show you the final project too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/11112021/sunoops.gif&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/11112021/sunoops2.gif&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p float=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/11112021/sunoops3.gif&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/11112021/sunoops5.gif&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-thoughts-on-frontend&quot;&gt;Some thoughts on frontend&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For no particular reason, I’ve been working on this project primarily in Typescript and not vanilla Javascript. Something I didn’t realize until I started actually working in Typescript is that the Typescript itself never actually gets executed. A program runs to transpile Typescript into Javascript and then the &lt;em&gt;Javascript&lt;/em&gt; gets executed. This is very different than the other approach of “add some types to this dynamic language” that I’ve used before, namely Hack. Hack actually runs on HHVM, it doesn’t first transpile into PHP to execute. The lack of runtime safety is a little disconcerting, especially in combination with this &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/microsoft/TypeScript/issues/27379&quot;&gt;bug I hit&lt;/a&gt; where &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tsc&lt;/code&gt; run on a single file doesn’t use your .tsconfig. (Hack also doesn’t have runtime safety though, but it’s not because it transpiles it into PHP).  If I got any of this wrong, lemme know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lost a day trying to understand how to use modules this week. There appear to be just so so many strategies and so many different concepts to understand. I eventually gave up and forked off of this great &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Gaweph/p5-typescript-starter&quot;&gt;starter project&lt;/a&gt; for using typescript with p5.js and manually added all the JS files I needed to my .html in a row like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;	&amp;lt;script src=&quot;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/p5@1.4.0/lib/p5.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
    	&amp;lt;script src=&quot;https://unpkg.com/p5.createloop@latest/dist/p5.createloop.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
    	&amp;lt;script src=&quot;./sketch/calc-azimuth-elev.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
    	&amp;lt;script src=&quot;./sketch/sketch.js&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe next week I’ll figure out how to use modules? I’d love to isolate my sun path calculations away from the sketches, of which I want to make many, but for now I think a separate file will work for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;programming-outside-of-work&quot;&gt;Programming outside of work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a treat to get to chat with friends about computers who I don’t work with! A few years ago, &lt;a href=&quot;twitter.com/niftynei&quot;&gt;Lisa&lt;/a&gt; worked on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://moon.supply/api.html&quot;&gt;moon clock&lt;/a&gt; and she’s been great to talk to about &lt;em&gt;Astronomical Algorithms&lt;/em&gt;, and the sun art I’ve been working on is inspired by seeing her IRL moon clock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RC has been a lovely way to see what other people are working on and how they approach their work. I had a bias/block against Processing after trying to use it in 2009, that I didn’t realize was rooted in 2009-era Java and not super relevant for how warm and welcoming it is to use now. Seeing people’s creative coding projects in the online editor made me take a closer look at it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re one of the people who’s been texting / messaging me about these blog posts, I’ve been really enjoying that!! It’s been great to talk to people while learning how to do things in frontend who know way way more about it than I do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Gosh, when did I last update y’all? It’s been a week! Here are some things I’ve been up to:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 2 &amp;amp; 3 at RC (‘How many days hath September?’)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/04/day2-3-rc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 2 &amp;amp; 3 at RC (‘How many days hath September?’)" /><published>2021-11-04T17:20:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-04T17:20:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/04/day2-3-rc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/04/day2-3-rc.html">&lt;p&gt;oh hi friends! When we last spoke it was day 1, and now it is the end of day 3. (RC was off for Election Day, so I too took off to sleep in and make some progress on Fall planting season).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working on my sun plotter project and meeting a few people 1-1 over Zoom!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;☀️ Sun plotter project:
I’ve been primarily working on computing azimuth/elevation based on lat/long/altitude/time of a location so that I can pass that into a lighting source in three.js to specify the &lt;em&gt;direction&lt;/em&gt; that light is coming from. Computing these two things has a closed form equation specified in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.agopax.it/Libri_astronomia/pdf/Astronomical%20Algorithms.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;Astronomical Algorithms&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as well as some published pages by &lt;a href=&quot;https://gml.noaa.gov/grad/solcalc/&quot;&gt;NOAA&lt;/a&gt; and other sources. I decided to port a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CIVA-Lab/solar-position-calculator&quot;&gt;library I found&lt;/a&gt; from C++ to JS directly to get some experience setting up a JS/Typescript project from scratch. My friend Tom pointed out that I could also use emscripten to compile to WebAssembly, which also seems like it could be cool to learn how to use later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway anyway, &lt;em&gt;did you know&lt;/em&gt; that all of these astronomical algorithms are specified in Julian time? I fell down a bit of a code reading rabbit hole trying to understand the Julian date conversions this C++ code was doing. Julian dates are also measured from noon to noon, and I’m not super sure if this library I found has a bug in it that makes it 12 hours off, BUT! if so, once I hook it up to my visualization I’m sure it will be quite easy to tell that it’s night when it’s supposed to be dark, ez.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relatedly, I have been thinking a bit about how to validate I get these calculations right. If I trust the library I’m porting more than I trust my ability to express math in javascript (yes), one thing I could do is write a small fuzzer program to send the same inputs to my program and that one and compare. I might do that just to double check my port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think accuracy is top of mind for me, as in the forward to &lt;em&gt;Astronomical Algorithms&lt;/em&gt; I read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People who write their own computer programs often wonder why the machine gives inaccurate planet positions, an unreal eclipse track, or a faulty Moon phase. Sometimes they insist, bewildered, ‘and I used double precision, too.’ Even commercial software is sometimes affllicted with gremlins, which comes as quite a shock to anyone caught up in the mystique and presumed infallibility of computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’m still working on that port, I’ve set up my Typescript project and wrangled npm and stubbed my functions and feel good about my code reading. I had a nice time talking to T in my batch about some &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;yargs&lt;/code&gt; details too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing I did was set up a WEBSITE so that you can see my spinning cube in three.js, and soon, the actual sun plotter, check it out here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://zmagg.com/sun-plotter&quot;&gt;https://zmagg.com/sun-plotter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ok that’s it for now, more tomorrow, ciao! I have more ideas about what to do with these sun algos once I have them implemented too… ☀️&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">oh hi friends! When we last spoke it was day 1, and now it is the end of day 3. (RC was off for Election Day, so I too took off to sleep in and make some progress on Fall planting season).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 1 (back) at Recurse Center!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/01/day-1-rc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 1 (back) at Recurse Center!" /><published>2021-11-01T12:47:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-01T12:47:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/01/day-1-rc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/11/01/day-1-rc.html">&lt;p&gt;First day back at RC!! I was last at RC in Summer 2013, over 8 years ago. I might want to ruminate on that some more later, but not now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I met a bunch of people, did onboarding, met my RC onboarding buddy, and started some organizing work for working through &lt;a href=&quot;https://greenteapress.com/wp/semaphores/&quot;&gt;The Little Book of Semaphores&lt;/a&gt; with a small crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, I set up some computing infrastructure stuff, including this blog! Hello world! Pretty delighted at how seamlessly project pages works with Github Pages–even the HTTPS was setup automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be doing RC on a Linux laptop that I haven’t used much, so there’s a ton of tiny dev environment details to figure out, on top of everything else. Today’s biggest nuisance (delight??) I ran into was setting up libsecret to store my GitHub personal access token in. After my initial setup, all my git commands would just hang forever. I delightedly used &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;strace&lt;/code&gt; and diagnosed that well, ok, I probably didn’t need to use strace to see that it was hanging on reading the credentials. Frustratedly fussed with chmod and reinstalling, until I found this helpful StackOverflow comment’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://askubuntu.com/questions/773455/what-is-the-correct-way-to-use-git-with-gnome-keyring-and-https-repos#comment2203681_959662&quot;&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt; and restarted my computer, and all was well. I suspect that since I was already using the Gnome keyring, I needed to kick it somehow after setting up libsecret, which restarting did for me. Would be curious to understand what actually happened though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project-wise I’m hoping to use three.js to build a sun mapper to visualize how the sun moves over the course of a day/year. I want to use this to help do garden planning :) so I’ll also need to figure out how to make a simple model of the houses in my neighborhood. Today I got started with some three.js tutorials and look! I made a cube and a DIRECTIONAL LIGHT that hits the CUBE. I’ll figure out how to deploy this tomorrow so I can share more than static images as I go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zmagg/blog/gh-pages/_posts/cube.gif&quot; alt=&quot;moving cube with light&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">First day back at RC!! I was last at RC in Summer 2013, over 8 years ago. I might want to ruminate on that some more later, but not now.</summary></entry></feed>